<!--

Copyright 2012 Double Precision, Inc.
See COPYING for distribution information.

-->

<chapter id="clusterhalt">
  <title>Halting an entire cluster</title>

  <para>
    &app; maintains transactional integrity of the cluster only as
    long as the cluster remains in &quorum;.
    A special process is necessary to shut down the entire cluster
    in a manner that preserves the object repository's transactional
    integrity. Stopping each node in the cluster is not sufficient.
    Eventually, the cluster will no longer be in quorum, and some
    clients may not longer have a reliable indication whether their
    transactions were posted, or not.
  </para>

  <para>
    Issuing the administrative <literal>HALT</literal> command
    stop all the nodes in a cluster, in a manner that preserves
    transactional integrity:
  </para>

  <informalexample>
    <computeroutput>
      <literallayout>[root@octopus stasher]# stasher
Ready, EOF to exit.
&gt; admin
Connected to objrepo.example.com, node octopus.objrepo.example.com.
Maximum 20 objects, 64 Mb aggregate object size, per transaction.
Maximum 10 concurrent subscriptions.
octopus> halt
Cannot halt the cluster, the cluster must be halted by monster.objrepo.example.com
octopus&gt;</literallayout>
    </computeroutput>
  </informalexample>

  <para>
    The <literal>HALT</literal> command must be issued to a node that's
    the cluster's current master node. This error message reports that
    another node in the cluster is the current master. The current
    cluster master is also reported by the <literal>STATUS</literal>
    command, too.
  </para>

  <informalexample>
    <computeroutput>
      <literallayout>[root@monster ~]# stasher
Ready, EOF to exit.
&gt; admin
Connected to objrepo.example.com, node monster.objrepo.example.com.
Maximum 20 objects, 64 Mb aggregate object size, per transaction.
Maximum 10 concurrent subscriptions.
monster> halt
Cluster is not in full quorum
monster&gt;</literallayout>
    </computeroutput>
  </informalexample>

  <para>
    The <literal>HALT</literal> command requires a &fullquorum;.
    This error message indicates that not all nodes are up,
    connected with each other, and fully synchronized. Use that
    <literal>STATUS</literal> command to display the cluster's
    current status, identify the unavailable nodes, and bring them
    back up. In order to preserve transaction integrity, all nodes
    in the cluster must be halted in full quorum, with each node's
    copy of the object repository identical to every other node's.
  </para>
    
  <informalexample>
    <computeroutput>
      <literallayout>monster&gt; halt
Cluster halted
Disconnected from monster.objrepo.example.com</literallayout>
    </computeroutput>
  </informalexample>

  <para>
    If all the requirements are met, the cluster gets halted. This
    stops all &app; node processes, on all the nodes.
  </para>
</chapter>
<!--
Local Variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->
